I'm really excited to share with you
يسعدني أن أشارككم
some findings that really surprise me
بعض النتائج المذهلة بالنسبة لي
about what makes companies succeed the most,
حول مايدفع الشركات للنجاح على أعلى مستوى،
what factors actually matter the most for startup success.
ما هي العوامل التي تؤثر في نجاح الشركات الناشئة،
I believe that the startup organization
أعتقد أن تنظيم الشركات الناشئة،
is one of the greatest forms to make the world a better place.
هي من أعظم الأساليب لجعل العالم مكان أفضل.
If you take a group of people with the right equity incentives
لو قمت بجمع بعض الناس و منحتهم حوافز عادلة
and organize them in a startup,
وقمت بتنظيمهم في شركة ناشئة،
you can unlock human potential in a way never before possible.
ستطلق طاقات بشرية كامنة بشكل لم يكن ممكن أبداً من قبل
You get them to achieve unbelievable things.
يمكنك دفعهم للوصول إلى نتائج مذهلة
But if the startup organization is so great,
و لكن إذا كان التنظيم للشركة الناشئة ممتاز،
why do so many fail?
لماذا يفشل الكثير منها؟
That's what I wanted to find out.
هذا ما أردت أن أعرفه.
I wanted to find out what actually matters most
أردت أن أعرف ماهو أهم عامل هنا
for startup success.
لنجاح الشركات الناشئة.
And I wanted to try to be systematic about it,
وأردت أن أكون منهجيا في ذلك،
avoid some of my instincts and maybe misperceptions I have
لأتفادى أي ميول مسبقة أو سوء إدراك عندي
from so many companies I've seen over the years.
من مشاهدة الكثير من الشركات خلال السنوات الماضية
I wanted to know this
أردت أن أعرف ذلك،
because I've been starting businesses since I was 12 years old
لأني بدأت أقوم بالأعمال التجارية منذ كان عمري 12 عاما.
when I sold candy at the bus stop in junior high school,
عندما كنت أبيع الحلوى عند مواقف الحافلات في المدرسة المتوسطة.
to high school, when I made solar energy devices,
وقمت بتصنيع أجهزة الطاقة الشمسية في المرحلة الثانوية
to college, when I made loudspeakers.
إلى الجامعة حيث قمت بتصنيع مكبرات الصوت
And when I graduated from college, I started software companies.
وعندما تخرجت من الجامعة بدأت شركات البرمجات
And 20 years ago, I started Idealab,
وقبل عشرون سنة بدأت شركة (Idealab)،
and in the last 20 years, we started more than 100 companies,
وفي العشرين سنة الأخيرة بدأنا بعمل أكثر من مائة شركة.
many successes, and many big failures.
كثير منها نجح، و كثير منها أخفق بشدة.
We learned a lot from those failures.
وتعلمنا الكثر من تلك الإخفاقات.
So I tried to look across what factors
وحاولت أن أستعرض العوامل
accounted the most for company success and failure.
التي أدت للنجاح والفشل في هذه الشركات
So I looked at these five.
لذا نظرت إلى تلك العوامل الخمسة.
First, the idea.
اولا، الفكرة
I used to think that the idea was everything.
لقد كنت اعتقد ان الفكرة هي كل شئ.
I named my company Idealab for how much I worship
فقد أسميت الشركة الخاصة (معمل الافكار) لإعجابي الشديد
the "aha!" moment when you first come up with the idea.
بتلك اللحظة التي تأتي بها بالفكرة لأول مرة
But then over time,
و لكن مع مرور الوقت
I came to think that maybe the team, the execution, adaptability,
وصلت بتفكيري الي أن ربما الفريق ، التنفيذ و القدرة علي التكيف
that mattered even more than the idea.
هذه الأشياء تعد اهم من الفكرة نفسها.
I never thought I'd be quoting boxer Mike Tyson on the TED stage,
لم اكن لأتخيل ابدا أني سأستشهد بمقولة الملاكم ( مايك تايسون ) علي منصة (TED)
but he once said,
لكنه قال يوما:
"Everybody has a plan, until they get punched in the face." (Laughter)
" كل منا لديه خطة، حتى يتلقى لكمة علي وجهه "
And I think that's so true about business as well.
و اظن أن هذا حقيقي و ينطبق علي المشاريع التجارية ايضا.
So much about a team's execution
جزء كبير من تنفيذ الفريق
is its ability to adapt to getting punched in the face by the customer.
يعتمد علي قدرته علي التكييف لتلقيه لكمة في الوجه من الزبون
The customer is the true reality.
الزبون هو الواقع الحقيقي
And that's why I came to think
و لهذا وصل بي التفكير
that the team maybe was the most important thing.
إلي أن ربما الفريق هو اهم عامل
Then I started looking at the business model.
بعد ذلك أخذت أدرس نموذج العمل
Does the company have a very clear path generating customer revenues?
هل لدى الشركة طريق واضح لإنتاج ايرادات للزبائن؟
That started rising to the top in my thinking
و هذا بدأ يعلو للقمة في تفكيري
about maybe what mattered most for success.
حول ما هي العوامل الأساسية للنجاح
Then I looked at the funding.
و بعد ذلك نظرت للتموين.
Sometimes companies received intense amounts of funding.
في بعض الاحيان تتلقي الشركات كميات هائلة من التموين.
Maybe that's the most important thing?
ربما هذا هو اهم عامل ؟
And then of course, the timing.
و بالطبع هناك التوقيت.
Is the idea way too early and the world's not ready for it?
هل الفكرة جاءت قبل معادها و العالم ليس مستعد لها ؟
Is it early, as in, you're in advance and you have to educate the world?
هل هي مبكرة، بحيث تكون في المقدمة و يجب عليك تعريف العالم بها ؟
Is it just right?
هل هي مثالية ؟
Or is it too late, and there's already too many competitors?
ام هي متأخرة، و هناك بالفعل العديد من المنافسون ؟
So I tried to look very carefully at these five factors
لذا حاولت أن أدرس بإتقان تلك العوامل الخمسة
across many companies.
خلال العديد من الشركات
And I looked across all 100 Idealab companies,
و بحثت في شركات معمل الأفكار المئة،
and 100 non-Idealab companies
وفي مئة أخرى غير تابعة لمعمل الشركات
to try and come up with something scientific about it.
لأحاول استنتاج فكرة علمية حول هذا الموضوع.
So first, on these Idealab companies,
اولا، في شركات معمل الأفكار،
the top five companies --
افضل خمس شركات :
Citysearch, CarsDirect, GoTo, NetZero, Tickets.com --
Citysearch, CarsDirect GoTo, NetZero, Tickets.com
those all became billion-dollar successes.
كل هؤلاء نجحوا بمليارات الدولارات.
And the five companies on the bottom --
و الخمس التي في الاسفل
Z.com, Insider Pages, MyLife, Desktop Factory, Peoplelink --
Z.com, Insider Pages, MyLife, Desktop Factory, Peoplelink
we all had high hopes for, but didn't succeed.
كانت آمالنا عالية تجاهها، و لكنها لم تنجح.
So I tried to rank across all of those attributes
لذا حاولت ان اصنف عبر كل السمات
how I felt those companies scored on each of those dimensions.
كيف شعرت حيال اداء الشركات في هذه العوامل.
And then for non-Idealab companies, I looked at wild successes,
و بالنسبة للشركات غير تابعة لمعمل الافكار، نظرت للنجاح المهول،
like Airbnb and Instagram and Uber and Youtube and LinkedIn.
مثل Airbnb, Instagram, Uber, Youtube و Linkedln
And some failures:
و بعض الإخفاقات :
Webvan, Kozmo, Pets.com
Webvan, Kozmo, Pets.com
Flooz and Friendster.
.Flooz and friendster
The bottom companies had intense funding,
الشركات بالأسفل كان لديها تمويل مكثف،
they even had business models in some cases,
و كان لديهم حتي نماذج العمل في بعض الحالات،
but they didn't succeed.
لكنهم لم ينجحوا.
I tried to look at what factors actually accounted the most
و لقد حاولت البحث عن العوامل
for success and failure across all of these companies,
التي أثرت في نجاح او اخفاق كل هذه الشركات،
and the results really surprised me.
و النتائج حقا فاجأتني.
The number one thing was timing.
العامل المؤثر الاول كان التوقيت.
Timing accounted for 42 percent
وضح التوقيت 42% من الفرق
of the difference between success and failure.
بين النجاح و الاخفاق.
Team and execution came in second,
الفريق و التنفيذ جاء في المرتبة الثانية،
and the idea,
و بعدهم الفكرة،
the differentiability of the idea, the uniqueness of the idea,
اختلاف الفكرة، تميز الفكرة،
that actually came in third.
ذلك جاء في المرتبة الثالثة
Now, this isn't absolutely definitive,
إن هذا ليس حاسم تماما،
it's not to say that the idea isn't important,
هذا لا يعني ان الفكرة ليست مهمة،
but it very much surprised me that the idea wasn't the most important thing.
لكن ما فاجأني حقا ان الفكرة لم تكن أهم عامل مؤثر.
Sometimes it mattered more when it was actually timed.
في بعض الاحيان كان الأهم هو التوقيت الصحيح.
The last two, business model and funding, made sense to me actually.
آخر اثنين، نموذج العمل و التمويل، كانوا منطقيين بالنسبة لي.
I think business model makes sense to be that low
في رأيي من المنطقي ان يكون نموذج العمل في مرتبة متدنية
because you can start out without a business model
لأن من الممكن ان تبدأ في مشروع بدون نموذج عمل
and add one later if your customers are demanding what you're creating.
و إضافته لاحقا اذا طالب الزبون بما تبتكره.
And funding, I think as well,
و بالنسبة للتمويل، في رأيي ايضا،
if you're underfunded at first but you're gaining traction,
اذا كنت تعاني من نقص التمويل في البداية ولكن تكتسب قوة جاذبة،
especially in today's age,
و خصوصا في عصرنا الحالي،
it's very, very easy to get intense funding.
من السهل جدا جدا أن تحصل علي التمويل المكثف
So now let me give you some specific examples about each of these.
اسمحوا لي أن أعطيكم بعض الأمثلة حول كل منهم.
So take a wild success like Airbnb that everybody knows about.
لنأخذ Airbnb كمثال لنجاح باهر الذي يعرفه الجميع.
Well, that company was famously passed on by many smart investors
حسنا، تلك الشركة عرفت بأنها مرت علي كثير من المستثمرين الاذكياء
because people thought,
لأن الناس كانوا يعتقدوا
"No one's going to rent out a space in their home to a stranger."
"لا أحد سيقوم بتأجير مكان داخل منزلهم لشخص غريب "
Of course, people proved that wrong.
بالطبع، أثبت الناس ان هذا الاعتقاد خاطئ.
But one of the reasons it succeeded,
لكن من اسباب نجاح ذلك المشروع
aside from a good business model, a good idea, great execution,
إلي جانب نموذج العمل الجيد، و فكرته الجيدة، و التنفيذ الممتاز،
is the timing.
هو التوقيت.
That company came out right during the height of the recession
تلك الشركة خرجت في قمة الفتور الإقتصادي
when people really needed extra money,
عندما كان الناس في أشد الاحتياج للنقود الإضافية،
and that maybe helped people overcome
و ربما ساعدهم ذلك في التغلب علي
their objection to renting out their own home to a stranger.
رفضهم لتأجير منزلهم الخاص لشخص غريب.
Same thing with Uber.
نفس الشئ مع Uber.
Uber came out,
Uber خرجت،
incredible company, incredible business model,
شركة مذهلة، نموذج عمل مذهل،
great execution, too.
تنفيذ ممتاز ايضا.
But the timing was so perfect
لكن التوقيت كان حقا مثالي
for their need to get drivers into the system.
لأنهم كانوا بحاجة إلي سائقين في منظومتهم.
Drivers were looking for extra money; it was very, very important.
و السائقين كانوا يبحثون عن نقود اضافية، و الذي كان في غاية الأهمية.
Some of our early successes, Citysearch, came out when people needed web pages.
بعض من النجاحات المبكرة، Citysearch، خرجت عندما كان الناس بحاجة إلي صفحات الويب.
GoTo.com, which we announced actually at TED in 1998,
GoTo.com، الذي تم الإعلان عنها في TED في 1998،
was when companies were looking for cost-effective ways to get traffic.
كان عندما الشركات تبحث طرق فعالة من حيث التكلفة للحصول علي حركة المرور.
We thought the idea was so great,
نحن ظننا أن الفكرة ممتازة،
but actually, the timing was probably maybe more important.
لكن في الحقيقة، كان التوقيت أكثر أهمية.
And then some of our failures.
و هنا أيضا بعد إخفاقاتنا.
We started a company called Z.com, it was an online entertainment company.
بدأنا شركة تدعي Z.com، وكانت شركة ترفيه علي الإنترنت.
We were so excited about it --
و كنا متحمسين جدا لها
we raised enough money, we had a great business model,
جمعنا الكم الكافي من النقود، كان لدينا نموذج عمل رائع،
we even signed incredibly great Hollywood talent to join the company.
و حتي عقدنا اتفاقات مع مواهب رائعة من Hollywood لتنضم بالشركة.
But broadband penetration was too low in 1999-2000.
لكن الاختراق على النطاق العريض كان منخفض للغاية في 1999-2000.
It was too hard to watch video content online,
كان من الصعب للغاية مشاهدة محتوى فيديو علي الإنترنت،
you had to put codecs in your browser and do all this stuff,
كان يجب أن تدخل الترميز علي المتصفح الخاص بك و تفعل كل هذه الأشياء
and the company eventually went out of business in 2003.
و في النهاية أفلست الشركة في 2003
Just two years later,
بعد سنتين،
when the codec problem was solved by Adobe Flash
عندما حلت مشكلة الترميز عن طريق Adobe Flash
and when broadband penetration crossed 50 percent in America,
و عندما عبر الاختراق علي النطاق العريض 50% من امريكا
YouTube was perfectly timed.
Youtube كان توقيته مثالي.
Great idea, but unbelievable timing.
فكرة رائعة، و لكن توقيت لا يصدق.
In fact, YouTube didn't even have a business model when it first started.
في الواقع، لم يكن لدي Youtube نموذج عمل عندما بدأت في البداية.
It wasn't even certain that that would work out.
لم يكن حتى من المؤكد أنها ستنجح.
But that was beautifully, beautifully timed.
لكنها كانت موقوتة بشكل حقا رائع.
So what I would say, in summary,
لذا ما أقوله في الخلاصة،
is execution definitely matters a lot.
أن التنفيذ حقا مهم،
The idea matters a lot.
الفكرة مهمة للغاية أيضا،
But timing might matter even more.
لكن التوقيت أكثر أهمية.
And the best way to really assess timing
و أفضل طريق للوصول للتوقيت الصحيح،
is to really look at whether consumers are really ready
هو النظر الدقيق، إذا كان المستهلكين حقا مستعدين
for what you have to offer them.
لما تقدمه لهم.
And to be really, really honest about it,
و تكن حقا صادقا في هذا،
not be in denial about any results that you see,
لا أن تنكر أي نتائج تراها،
because if you have something you love, you want to push it forward,
لأنك إذا لديك شئ تحبه، و تريد أن تدفعه للأمام،
but you have to be very, very honest about that factor on timing.
يجب أن تكون حقا صادقا في عامل التوقيت.
As I said earlier,
كما قلت سابقا،
I think startups can change the world and make the world a better place.
أظن أن الشركات الناشئة تستطيع أن تغير العالم و تجعله مكان افضل.
I hope some of these insights
أتمني أن بعض من هذه الرؤي
can maybe help you have a slightly higher success ratio,
قد ربما تساعدكم في الحصول علي نسبة نجاح أعلي،
and thus make something great come to the world
و بالتالي تصنع شئ رائع ليأتي إالي العالم.
that wouldn't have happened otherwise.
والذي لم يكن ليحدث بطريقة أخري.
Thank you very much, you've been a great audience.
شكرا جزيلا لكم، لقد كنتم جمهور رائع.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)